NIRANJAN GANESAN PHONE: +44 (0) 7308 16 1523

Email: niranjan27494@gmail.com Website: www.niranjanganesan.com

Software Engineer with 3.5 years of experience in development, operations, testing and support to consumer applications. Highly analytical and process-oriented individual with in-depth knowledge of data mining, data modelling, statistical analysis, business intelligence gathering; with the ability to solve challenging business problems and deliver valuable insights.

EXPERIENCE

LOTUS PROJECT - DATA SCIENCE INTERN.

JUN 2020 - AUG 2020

- Data Exploration of Economics and Development data.
- Access structure and store the data on AWS relational database server.
- Develop a framework to support the collection, retrieval and structuring of internal data generated by Rural Development Model.
- Provide key metrics and develop Machine Learning scoring algorithms to assess the economic and environmental impact of rapidly growing nations or rural areas.
- Incorporate the results of the data analysis to a geoJSON and JSON file format to visualize the results on a global map using google maps platform.

IBM – SOFTWARE DEVELOPER (CONTR.)

FEB 2018 – AUG 2019

- Collaborate with key stakeholders in gathering the requirements for data analysis.
- Software Development using Agile practices and report progress to clients over daily scrum call.
- Proficient in data modelling and successful in identifying patterns, trends in datasets.
- In depth analysis of metrics and indicators responsible for modelling the data.
- Excellent capability to explore, learn and understand newer business domains and technologies.
- Creation of data dashboards, graphs and visualizations.
- Proficient in preparing and executing test cases, system integration testing, unit testing, user acceptance testing and functional testing.
- Handle huge volumes of customer data on relational database management systems; Guiding and teaching junior colleagues on new projects.

CAPGEMINI – SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

OCT 2015 - SEP 2017

- Business requirements gathering with key stakeholders and clients for data analysis.
- Data extraction from various data sources, understand and document detailed business requirements using appropriate tools and techniques.
- Project estimation with clients and developers.
- Prepare periodical daily, weekly and monthly reports for ongoing projects.
- Follow Agile methodology and report progress to clients over daily scrum call.
- Identify areas to increase efficiency and automation of processes.

EDUCATION

MSc BIG DATA SCIENCE - QUEEN MARY UNIVERSITY OF LONDON

2019 - 2020

Relevant Modules – Data Mining, Applied Statistics, Big Data Processing, Machine Learning, Cloud Computing, Deep Learning and Computer Vision, Data Analytics, Machine Learning for Visual Data Analysis.

BEng ELECTRONICS AND COMMUNICATION ENGINEERING (1st Equivalent) - ANNA UNIVERSITY, INDIA 2011 – 2015

Relevant Modules - Computer Networks, Digital Signal Processing, Wireless Networks, Digital Electronics, Wireless communications, Signals and Systems. **CGPA – 7.27/10**

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Experience with Big data technologies such as Apache Hadoop, Kafka, HDFS command line tool and Spark.
- Proficient in back-end python coding, building Flask web applications.
- Building ML apps and deploying in cloud platform using Docker, Kubernetes., etc.
- Software Development using Agile practices and waterfall method.
- Performing statistical analysis on collected data to identify critical trends and conditions.
- Data Analytics with proficient SQL language skill.
- Skilled communicator, able to influence across boundaries.
- Providing hands-on analysis, programming, configuration, testing and implementation support to assigned systems and/or projects.
- Immediate response to critical issues, fixing critical software issues with minimal or no business impact as soon as possible.

- Data Analysis
- Data Visualization
- Machine Learning
- Python
- Java Script
- Kafka
- Hadoop
- NoSQL
- Spark
- Cloud Computing
- AWS
- Rest API
- Docker
- Data Science
- Spark RDD
- Flask

PROJECTS AND CERTIFICATIONS

• Big Data Analysis on Ethereum Blockchain

The objective of this project is to analyze the big datasets of Ethereum Blockchain data and derive insights from it using Big Data tools such as Hadoop and Spark using HDFS architecture. Time Analysis – number of transactions every month, Top 10 most popular services, Exploratory Data Analysis on gas, scams and more.

Github Link - https://github.com/niranjanganesan/Big-Data

COVID-19 Web Application – Cloud Computing

The objective of this project is to build an analytics dashboard which is a prototype of Cloud Application developed in Python and Flask web framework that gives the global statistics of affected cases. This App makes use of a REST API service to get the daily statistics of COVID-19 and the application is containerized with Kubernetes load balancing service deployed in the AWS EC2 instance.

Github Link - https://github.com/niranjanganesan/ECS781P Cloud Computing Mini Project

• IBM Certified Data Science Professional

OTHER ROLES OF RESPONSIBILITY

- Music, Theatre and Dance Trained Professional dancer with numerous stage performances over the period of 8 years.
- Media and Technical skills Audio and video editor for college promotional and cultural videos. Photo editor for College Newsletter.
- Leadership Class representative for two consecutive years at my undergraduate university.
- Entrepreneurship Sales and Marketing apprentice for an event management startup.
- Sports Member of football committee at my undergraduate university.
- Volunteering Member of Backstage organizing crew for various dance and arts performances.

REFERENCES AVAILABLE ON REQUEST